<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<newspaper_histories>
		<title>Browse Newspaper Titles</title>
		<meta name="description">Full text searchable scans of some of the oldest newspapers in Canada</meta>
		<credits lang="en">The short newspaper descriptions were written by Edith Burley and Lynne Champagne.</credits>
		<credits lang="fr">Les courtes descriptions des journaux furent &#233;crites par Edith Burley et Lynne Champagne.</credits>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Nor'Wester (1859)</name>
        <sortName>Nor'Wester 1859</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>NWR</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="12" day="28" year="1859"/>
            <end month="11" day="23" year="1869"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr"> The Nor'Wester, le premier journal du Manitoba, a été publié du 28
            décembre 1859 au 28 septembre 1869. Son prospectus, publié le 22 août 1859, promettait
            que le journal ferait valoir les intérêts locaux et rapporterait tous les faits sans
            parti pris. Sa fréquence de publication variait; il paraissait à toutes les semaines ou
            deux. Il a été supprimé par les partisans de Louis Riel et fusionné avec le Red River
            Pioneer pour devenir The New Nation. </history>
        <history lang="en">The Nor'Wester, Manitoba’s first newspaper, was published from December
            28, 1859 until September 28, 1869. The prospectus, published August 22, 1859, promised
            the newspaper would promote local interests and report all events impartially. Its
            publication frequency varied; it was published weekly or biweekly. It was suppressed by
                <persName>Louis Riel</persName>’s supporters and was merged with the Red River
            Pioneer to become The New Nation.</history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Nor'Wester (1874)</name>
        <sortName>Nor'Wester 1874</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>NOR</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="6" day="29" year="1874"/>
            <end month="12" day="21" year="1875"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Nor'Wester a été publié quotidiennement du 8 décembre 1874 au 5
            avril 1875. Son rédacteur en chef était le marchand et auteur Alexander Begg. Il
            appuyait le gouvernement provincial Davis, élu en décembre 1874.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Nor'Wester, published daily from December 8, 1874 to April 5, 1875
            was edited by Alexander Begg, merchant and author. It supported the Davis provincial
            government which was elected in December 1874. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Manitoba Gazette</name>
        <sortName>Manitoba Gazette</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>MGZ</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="10" day="12" year="1878"/>
            <end month="3" day="15" year="1879"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Manitoba Gazette était un hebdomadaire qui a paru du 12 octobre 1878
            au 15 mars 1879. Se proclamant libéral-conservateur, il s’opposait au gouvernement
            provincial au pouvoir. Il a cessé de paraître après avoir été poursuivi en justice pour
            diffamation. </history>
        <history lang="en">The Manitoba Gazette was a weekly that appeared from October 12, 1878
            until March 15, 1879. It claimed to be Liberal-Conservative and an opposed to the
            current provincial government. It ceased publication after being sued for
        libel.</history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Standard</name>
        <sortName>Standard</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>STD</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="11" day="28" year="1874"/>
            <end month="8" day="30" year="1879"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Standard a paru une fois par semaine du 28 novembre 1874 au 30 août
            1879. Le tracé proposé du chemin de fer du Canadien Pacifique et les concessions
            foncières aux Métis sont quelques-uns des sujets qui ont été discutés à fond dans ses
            pages. Il s’appelait préalablement le Manitoban and Northwest Herald.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Standard appeared weekly from November 28, 1874 until August 30,
            1879. Among the issues discussed at great length in its pages were the proposed route of
            the CPR and Métis land grants. Its previous title was the Manitoban and Northwest
            Herald.</history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Manitoba Herald</name>
        <sortName>Manitoba Herald</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>MHD</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="1" day="11" year="1877"/>
            <end month="8" day="2" year="1877"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Manitoba Herald a été publié quotidiennement du 11 janvier 1877 au 2
            août 1877. Son intention était de défendre les intérêts du Manitoba et de surveiller le
            comportement des représentants de la province.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Manitoba Herald was published daily from January 11, 1877 until
            August 2, 1877. Its intention was to defend the interests of Manitoba and to keep an eye
            on the behaviour of the province’s representatives.</history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Quiz</name>
        <sortName>Quiz</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>QUZ</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="10" day="19" year="1878"/>
            <end month="6" day="7" year="1879"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Quiz a paru du 19 octobre 1878 au 7 juin 1879. Déclarant qu’il
            jouerait le rôle de fou du roi, le journal, pendant sa courte vie, s’est moqué des
            citoyens en vue de Winnipeg et a commenté, parfois sarcastiquement, la politique
            nationale.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Quiz appeared from October 19, 1878 until June 7, 1879. It declared
            that it would play the role of jester and during its short existence it poked fun at
            prominent citizens of Winnipeg and commented, sometimes sarcastically, on national
            politics. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Manitoba News-Letter</name>
        <sortName>Manitoba News-Letter</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>MNL</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="9" day="13" year="1870"/>
            <end month="7" day="1" year="1871"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Manitoba News-Letter appartenait à John Christian Schultz et a été
            publié deux fois par semaine du 30 septembre 1870 au 1er juillet 1871. Anti-catholique
            et pro-canadien, il était violemment opposé aux partisans du gouvernement provisoire.
            Après avoir été vendu à la Manitoba Printing Company, le journal a reparu sous le nom de
            Manitoba Liberal.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Manitoba News-Letter belonged to John Christian Schultz and was
            published twice a week from September 30, 1870 to July 1, 1971. It was anti-Catholic and
            pro-Canadian and a violent opponent of supporters of the provisional government. After
            it was sold to the Manitoba Printing Company, the paper reappeared as The Manitoba
            Liberal.</history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Red River Pioneer</name>
        <sortName>Red River Pioneer</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>RRP</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="12" day="1" year="1869"/>
            <end month="12" day="1" year="1869"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Red River Pioneer a paru une seule fois, le 1er décembre 1869, avant
            d’être vendu et fusionné avec le Nor’Wester pour devenir The New Nation.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Red River Pioneer appeared only once, on Dec 1, 1869, before it was
            sold and merged with the Nor’Wester to become the New Nation. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>New Nation</name>
				<sortName>New Nation</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>NNT</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="1" day="7" year="1870"/>
            <end month="9" day="3" year="1870"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The New Nation a été publié une fois par semaine du 7 janvier 1870 au 3
            septembre 1870. Formé par la fusion du Red River Pioneer et du Nor’Wester, il était
            l’organe du gouvernement provisoire dirigé par Louis Riel. Il rapportait avec amples
            détails les débats et délibérations du gouvernement provisoire.</history>
        <history lang="en">The New Nation was published weekly from January 7, 1870 to September 3,
            1870. Formed by the merger of the Red River Pioneer with the Nor'Wester, it was an organ
            of the provisional government headed by Louis Riel. It reported in great detail the
            debates and discussions of the provisional government. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="fr">
        <name>Courrier du Nord-Ouest</name>
        <sortName>Courrier du Nord-Ouest</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>CNO</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="5" day="31" year="1888"/>
            <end month="12" day="27" year="1888"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">Cet hebdomadaire qui n’a pas fait long feu (mai à décembre 1888) a été
            fondé à Saint-Boniface par James Prendergast, secrétaire provincial du nouveau
            gouvernement libéral de Thomas Greenway. Son rédacteur en chef était l’ancien député
            fédéral de Sainte-Agathe, Ernest Cyr. Établi en réponse au besoin d’un journal politique
            français pour le Parti libéral provincial, le journal n’a pas réussi à gagner l’appui de
            la population résolument conservatrice de Saint-Boniface et a disparu après la défaite
            de Cyr à l’élection provinciale de juin 1888.</history>
        <history lang="en">This short-lived weekly newspaper (May to December 1888) was founded in
            St. Boniface by James Prendergast, Provincial Secretary in the newly-formed Liberal
            government under Thomas Greenway. The editor was former M.P. for Ste. Agathe, Ernest
            Cyr. Its publication was in response to a need for a French language political newspaper
            for the provincial Liberal party. The newspaper could not gain the support of the
            staunchly Conservative population of St. Boniface, and disappeared following Cyr’s
            defeat in the provincial election in June 1888.</history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Manitoban and Northwest Herald</name>
        <sortName>Manitoban and Northwest Herald</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>TWM</code>
            <code>TMB</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="10" day="15" year="1870"/>
            <end month="11" day="21" year="1874"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Manitoban and Northwest Herald a paru une fois par semaine du 15
            octobre 1870 au 21 novembre 1874, quoique sa publication ait été suspendue du 21
            septembre au 23 novembre 1872. Du 19 novembre 1870 au 14 septembre 1872, il s’est appelé
            The Weekly Manitoban and Herald of Rupert’s Land and North-Western Territory. Il a été
            continué par The Standard.</history>
        <history lang="en"> The Manitoban and Northwest Herald appeared weekly from October 15,
            1870 until November 21, 1874, though its publication was suspended from September 21 -
            November 23, 1872. From November 19, 1870 until September 14, 1872, its title changed to
            the Weekly Manitoban and Herald of Rupert's Land and North-Western Territory. It was
            continued by the Standard. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Manitoba Liberal</name>
        <sortName>Manitoba Liberal</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>TML</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="7" day="12" year="1871"/>
            <end month="5" year="1873"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Manitoba Liberal a été établi après la vente du Manitoba News-Letter
            à la Manitoba Printing Company. Le 1er juillet 1871, le News-Letter a annoncé qu’il
            serait remplacé par le Liberal et exhorté ses lecteurs à s’y abonner. Le Liberal a paru
            une fois par semaine du 12 juillet 1871 à mai 1873 et a continué sous le nom de
            Nor’Wester en 1874.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Manitoba Liberal was established after the sale of the Manitoba
            News-Letter to the Manitoba Printing Company. On July 1, 1871, the News-Letter announced
            that it would be replaced by the Liberal and urged its readers to subscribe to it. The
            Liberal appeared weekly from July 12, 1871 until May 1873 and was continued by the
            Nor’Wester in 1874. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Winnipeg Daily Sun</name>
        <sortName>Winnipeg Daily Sun</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>WSN</code>
            <code>TSN</code>
            <code>WDS</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="8" day="17" year="1881"/>
            <end month="7" day="4" year="1885"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Winnipeg Daily Sun a été publié six fois par semaine du 17 août 1881
            au 4 juillet 1885. Il a été un des nombreux journaux éphémères qui se sont fait
            concurrence à Winnipeg dans les années 1880.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Winnipeg Daily Sun was published six times a week from August 17,
            1881 until July 4, 1885. It was one of the many short-lived newspapers that competed for
            readers in Winnipeg during the 1880s.</history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Daily Nor'Wester</name>
        <sortName>Daily Nor'Wester</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>DNW</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="2" day="3" year="1894"/>
            <end month="6" day="8" year="1898"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Daily Nor’Wester a été publié six jours par semaine (tous les jours
            sauf le dimanche) du 3 février 1894 au 8 juin 1898. Son prospectus a paru le 29 décembre
            1893. Il a été fondé par W. F. Luxton, qui a aussi fondé le Manitoba Free Press. Luxton
            a vendu le Daily Nor’Wester en 1896 et sous une nouvelle direction, le journal a publié
            une édition du matin et une édition du soir du 2 janvier 1897 au 8 juin 1898. <br/> Il
            est devenu The Morning Telegram le 9 juin 1898. </history>
        <history lang="en">The Daily Nor'Wester was published six times a week (except Sundays)
            from February 3, 1894 to June 8, 1898. Prospectus Dec. 29, 1893. It was started by W.F.
            Luxton, the founder of the Manitoba Free Press. Luxton sold the Daily Nor'Wester in 1896
            and under new ownership, morning and evening editions were published from January 2,
            1897 to June 8, 1898. <br/> It was continued as the Morning Telegram on June 9, 1898.
        </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Morning Telegram</name>
        <sortName>Morning Telegram</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>TMT</code>
            <code>TTG</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="6" day="9" year="1898"/>
            <end month="8" day="21" year="1907"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Morning Telegram a été publié tous les jours de la semaine sauf le
            dimanche du 9 juin 1898 au 21 août 1907. Il était la continuation du Daily Nor’Wester
            (1894) et a été continué par The Winnipeg Telegram. Un numéro spécial du journal appelé
            The Winnipeg Women's Paper a été publié gracieusement par le Morning Telegram le 8 mai
            1907. Ses articles ont été réimprimés en 1929 dans un livret intitulé Pioneer Winnipeg
            Women's Work, par Minnie J. B. Campbell. C'est cette deuxième version qui a été
            numérisée car aucun exemplaire intégral de l'original du 8 mai 1907 ne semble exister. </history>
        <history lang="en">The Morning Telegram was published six times a week except Sundays from
            June 9, 1898 until August 21, 1907. It was a continuation of the Daily Nor’Wester (1894)
            and was continued by the Winnipeg Telegram. A special edition of the newspaper known as
            the Winnipeg Women's Paper was published courtesy of the Morning Telegram on May 8,
            1907. Its articles were reprinted in 1929 as a booklet entitled Pioneer Winnipeg Women's
            Work by Minnie J. B. Campbell. It is this second version which was digitized as no
            complete copy of the original issue of May 8, 1907 is known to exist. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>The People's Voice</name>
        <sortName>People's Voice</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>TPV</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="6" day="16" year="1894"/>
            <end month="5" day="1" year="1897"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The People’s Voice a été publié une fois par semaine du 16 juin 1894 au
            1er mai 1897. Conçu comme organe du Winnipeg Trades and Labor Council, il est devenu le
            plus important journal ouvrier de l’Ouest canadien. Après avoir été vendu à The Voice
            Publishing Company, il a été remplacé par The Voice.</history>
        <history lang="en">The People’s Voice was published weekly from June 16, 1894 until May 1,
            1897. Intended to be the organ of the Winnipeg Trades and Labor Council, it became the
            most important labour newspaper in western Canada. After being sold to The Voice
            Publishing Company, it was replaced by The Voice. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>The Voice</name>
        <sortName>Voice</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>TVC</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="5" day="8" year="1897"/>
            <end month="7" day="26" year="1918"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Voice a remplacé The People’s Voice. Il a paru une fois par semaine
            du 8 mai 1897 au 26 juillet 1918. Son rédacteur en chef était Arthur Puttee, un
            socialiste modéré. Mais le Trades and Labor Council l’a trouvé trop modéré et a dissous
            le journal pour le réorganiser sous le nom de The Western Labor News.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Voice replaced The People’s Voice. It appeared weekly from May 8,
            1897 until July 26, 1918. Its editor was Arthur Puttee, a moderate socialist. But the
            Trades and Labor Council found him too moderate and the paper was dissolved and
            reorganized as The Western Labor News. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Minnedosa Tribune</name>
        <sortName>Minnedosa Tribune</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>MDT</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="3" day="31" year="1883"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Minnedosa Tribune est publié une fois par semaine depuis le 31 mars
            1883. Il était un des nombreux petits journaux ruraux qui ont vu le jour au début des
            années 1880, mais il est un des rares à avoir duré jusqu’au vingt-et-unième siècle.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Minnedosa Tribune has been published weekly since March 31, 1883. It
            was one of many small rural newspapers that appeared in the early 1880s, but it is one
            of the few that lasted into the twenty-first century. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Portage la Prairie Weekly</name>
        <sortName>Portage la Prairie Weekly</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>WTM</code>
            <code>PTR</code>
            <code>PWR</code>
            <code>PRV</code>
            <code>PHJ</code>
            <code>PNR</code>
            <code>PTN</code>
            <code>PDN</code>
            <code>PWN</code>
            <code>PRV</code>
            <code>PER</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="9" day="9" year="1881"/>
            <end month="9" day="6" year="1916"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">
            <p>Ce journal a paru pour la première fois le 9 septembre 1881 pour une période de 35
                ans jusqu'à son dernier numéro du 6 septembre 1916. Pour la grande partie de son
                existence, ce fut un hebdomadaire avec l'exception de deux courtes périodes où les
                numéros parurent deux ou trois fois par semaine. Les résidants de Portage La Prairie
                le connurent sous plusieurs noms différents, lesquels suivent ici en ordre
                chronologique. </p>
            <p> Il parût pour la première fois sous le titre Portage la Prairie Weekly Tribune, le 9
                septembre 1881. Celui-ci absorba le journal Marquette Review and Portage Times le 8
                février 1884 et jusqu'au 29 août 1884, il fut publié sous le nouveau titre Portage
                la Prairie Weekly Tribune and Marquette Review. Malheureusement seulement les
                numéros de 1884 existent. Portage la Prairie Weekly Tribune-Review fut publié du 5
                septembre 1884 jusqu’au 4 novembre 1887. Portage la Prairie Weekly Review fut publié
                du 11 novembre 1887 au 22 décembre 1898. Portage la Prairie News and Portage la
                Prairie Review fut publié du 2 février 1899 et s’est terminée le 26 novembre 1902.
                Il a été publié une fois par semaine, à l’exception de la période du 4 octobre 1899
                au 13 mai 1901, pendant laquelle il a été publié 3 fois par semaine. Portage la
                Prairie News fut publié une fois par semaine du 3 décembre 1902 au 29 juin 1904.
                Portage la Prairie Semi-Weekly News fut publié deux fois par semaine du 8 juillet
                1904 au 9 janvier 1906. Portage la Prairie Review fut publié chaque mardi et
                vendredi du 10 janvier 1906 jusqu'au 30 mars 1906. Portage la Prairie Weekly Review
                (1906) fut publié du 6 janvier 1906 jusqu’au 6 septembre 1916. </p>
        </history>
        <history lang="en">
            <p> This newspaper was first published on September 9, 1881 for a period of 35 years
                until its last issue on September 6, 1916. During its long existence it was a weekly
                publication with the exception of two short stints of semi-weekly or thrice weekly
                issues. Portage La Prairie residents knew it by many different titles, listed below
                in chronological order. </p>
            <p> It began as the <b>Portage la Prairie Weekly Tribune</b>, first issued on September
                9, 1881. The Tribune absorbed another newspaper, the <b>Marquette Review and Portage
                    Times</b> on February 8, 1884 and until August 29, 1884 published under the new
                title <b>Portage la Prairie Weekly Tribune and Marquette Review</b>. Unfortunately
                of this early period, only the 1884 issues are known to exist. <b>Portage la Prairie
                    Weekly Tribune-Review</b> was published September 5, 1884 to November 4, 1887.
                    <b>Portage la Prairie Weekly Review was published November 11, 1887 to December
                    22, 1898. Portage la Prairie News and Portage la Prairie Review</b> was
                published from February 2, 1899 to November 26, 1902. Published weekly except for
                the period from October 4, 1899 to May 13, 1901 when it was published 3 times
                weekly. <b>Portage la Prairie News</b> was published weekly from December 3, 1902
                until June 29, 1904. <b>Portage la Prairie Semi-Weekly News</b> was published from
                July 8, 1904 until January 9, 1906. <b>Portage la Prairie Review</b> was then
                published every Tuesday and Friday from January 10 - March 30 1906. <b>Portage la
                    Prairie Weekly Review</b> (1906) was published from April 4, 1906 until
                September 6, 1916. </p>
        </history>
    </newspaper>
		<newspaper lang="en">
			<name>Brandon Daily Sun</name>
			<sortName>Brandon Daily Sun</sortName>
			<codes>
				<code>BDS</code>
			</codes>
			<pubDates>          
				<start month="1" day="1" year="1882"/>
				<end month="12" day="31" year="1960"/>
			</pubDates>
			<history lang="en">The Brandon Daily Sun began publication in 1882 and appeared until 1884 when it was replaced by the Brandon Weekly Sun. In 1897, the Daily Sun reappeared and soon became the newspaper of record for Brandon and south western Manitoba, until it was succeeded by the Brandon Sun in       1960.</history>
			<history lang="fr">Le Brandon Daily Sun, débuta en 1882 et parut jusqu'en 1884 lorsqu'il fut remplacé par le Brandon Weekly Sun.  En 1897, le      Daily Sun recommença à être publié and devint bientôt le registre des évènements pour Brandon et le sud-ouest du Manitoba, jusqu'à  ce que le Brandon Sun lui donna suite en 1960.</history>
		</newspaper>

    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Brandon Sun Weekly</name>
        <sortName>Brandon Sun Weekly</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>BSN</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="1" day="19" year="1882"/>
            <end month="7" day="1" year="1897"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Brandon Sun Weekly a commencé à paraître le 19 janvier 1882, alors
            que la ville de Brandon n’était guère plus qu’une collection de tentes. Malgré tout, le
            journal a eu du succès et a duré jusqu’au 1er juillet 1897. Peu de temps après, un
            nouveau Sun quotidien a été établi, qui est publié encore aujourd’hui.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Brandon Sun Weekly began publication on January 19, 1882, when the
            city of Brandon was hardly more than a collection of tents. Nevertheless, the newspaper
            did well and continued until July 1, 1897. Soon after a new daily Sun was established
            and is still published today. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="fr">
        <name>La Liberté</name>
        <sortName>La Liberté</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>LLT</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="5" day="20" year="1913"/>
            <end/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">Fondé par Adélard Langevin, archevêque de Saint-Boniface, La Liberté a
            publié son premier numéro le 20 mai 1913 et est le plus vieil hebdomadaire français au
            Manitoba. Journal engagé, La Liberté était la voix de la population francophone du
            Manitoba et le défenseur de ses droits linguistiques et religieux, et il a fini par
            forcer ses principaux rivaux, Le Manitoba et Le Soleil de l’Ouest, à cesser de publier.
            Publié encore aujourd’hui, il se concentre principalement sur les nouvelles et
            informations qui intéressent les francophones de la province.</history>
        <history lang="en">Manitoba’s longest-running French-language weekly, La Liberté was
            founded by Adélard Langevin, Archbishop of St. Boniface, and first appeared May 20,
            1913. A crusading newspaper, La Liberté was the voice of the French-speaking population
            of Manitoba and defender of its linguistic and religious rights, forcing its principal
            rivals, Le Manitoba and Le Soleil de l’Ouest, to eventually cease publication. Still
            published today, its focus is on news and information for the province's francophones.
        </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="fr">
        <name>Le Métis</name>
        <sortName>Le Métis</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>LMT</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="5" day="27" year="1871"/>
            <end month="9" day="29" year="1881"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">Fondé le 27 mai 1871 par Joseph Royal, un avocat et journaliste né au
            Québec, et édité par Royal et Joseph Dubuc, Le Métis a été le premier hebdomadaire
            français de la province. Il a été publié régulièrement jusqu’au 29 septembre 1881, puis
            remplacé par Le Manitoba. Journal conservateur, il visait à défendre les droits fonciers
            des Métis, encourager l’immigration canadienne française au Manitoba et promouvoir le
            fédéralisme et la cause catholique française.</history>
        <history lang="en">Founded May 27, 1871 by Québec-born lawyer and journalist Joseph Royal
            and edited by Royal and Joseph Dubuc, Le Métis was the province’s first French-language
            weekly newspaper. It was published regularly until September 29, 1881 when it was
            replaced by Le Manitoba. A Conservative newspaper, it sought to defend Métis land
            rights, encourage French-Canadian immigration to Manitoba, and promote federalism and
            the French-Catholic cause. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="fr">
        <name>Le Manitoba</name>
        <sortName>Le Manitoba</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>LMJ</code>
            <code>LMS</code>
            <code>LMB</code>
            <code>LMD</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="10" day="13" year="1881"/>
            <end year="1925"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">
            <p> Le Manitoba a pris la relève du Métis en 1881, son nouveau titre reflétant
                l’évolution de la démographie de la province. Il a disparu en 1925, perdant une
                bataille durement menée contre l’hebdomadaire conservateur soutenu par l’Église, La
                Liberté. </p>
            <p> Du 13 octobre 1881 au 15 octobre 1882 inclusivement, il a publié une édition
                hebdomadaire. Du 26 octobre 1882 au 18 octobre 1883, il a été publié sous forme
                bihebdomadaire seulement. Pendant une courte période, soit du 18 octobre 1883 au 10
                janvier 1884, il a publié à la fois une édition hebdomadaire et une édition
                bihebdomadaire. Du 17 janvier 1884 à 1925, il a été publié seulement une fois par
                semaine. </p>
        </history>
        <history lang="en">
            <p> Le Manitoba took over from Le Métis in 1881 its new title reflecting the changing
                demographic make-up of the province. It disappeared in 1925, losing a hard-fought
                battle against the Church-supported Conservative weekly, La Liberté. </p>
            <p> Weekly editions are available from October 13, 1881 to October 5, 1882 inclusive. It
                is published in a semi weekly format only from October 26, 1882 to October 18, 1883.
                For a short period, October 18, 1883 to January 10, 1884, it is published in both
                semi weekly and weekly editions. From January 17, 1884 until 1925, it is published
                weekly only. </p>
        </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="fr">
        <name>Ouest Canadien</name>
        <sortName>Ouest Canadien</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>OCD</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="2" day="14" year="1889"/>
            <end month="8" day="14" year="1889"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">Le Courrier de l’Ouest a été publié une fois par semaine à
            Saint-Boniface du 14 février au 14 août 1889, après quoi Prendergast a quitté le cabinet
            libéral à cause des plans du gouvernement d’abolir le bilinguisme officiel et le
            financement provincial des écoles confessionnelles.</history>
        <history lang="en">Le Courrier de l’Ouest was published weekly in St. Boniface from
            February 14 to August 14, 1889, when Prendergast left the Liberal cabinet because of the
            government’s plans to abolish official bilingualism and provincial funding to
            denominational schools. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="fr">
        <name>Libre Parole</name>
        <!--<name>Libre Parole 1916-1919</name>-->
        <sortName>Libre Parole</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>LPR</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="3" day="9" year="1916"/>
            <end year="1919"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">
            La Libre Parole, un hebdomadaire, a commencé le 4 mai 1916. De plus 
            grand format et de composition plus soignée que ses prédécesseurs, ce 
            journal libéral n’a pas réussi à concurrencer ses rivaux conservateurs 
            Le Manitoba et La Liberté et a cessé de paraître en 1919.
            <br/>    
            La collection numérisée va jusqu’au numéro du 20 septembre 1917.
            
        </history>
        <history lang="en">
            <p> La Libre parole, a weekly, started May 4, 1916. Larger and more carefully laid-out
                than its predecessors, this Liberal newspaper could not compete with its
                Conservative rivals Le Manitoba and La Liberté and ceased publication in 1919. </p>
            <p> This digitized collection ends with the September 20, 1917 issue.</p>
        </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="fr">
        <name>Echo du Manitoba</name>
        <sortName>Echo du Manitoba</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>LDM</code>
            <code>EDM</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="1" day="27" year="1898"/>
            <end month="7" day="20" year="1905"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">Hebdomadaire fondé le 27 janvier 1898 par un groupe de libéraux dont le
            député fédéral de Morris Alphonse Martin, l’Écho du Manitoba avait un but précis. La
            victoire de Laurier au fédéral et le compromis Laurier-Greenway de 1897 avaient
            revitalisé le Parti libéral francophone au Manitoba, qui avait besoin d’un organe
            officiel. Son programme était simple : « Notre race, notre langue, notre religion ». Le
            dernier numéro a paru le 20 juillet 1905, quand son rédacteur en chef Henri
            d’Hellencourt a quitté le Manitoba pour le Québec.</history>
        <history lang="en">A weekly founded January 27, 1898 by a group of Liberals including
            Morris M.P. Alphonse Martin, l’Écho du Manitoba had a specific goal. Laurier’s victory
            at the federal level and the Laurier-Greenway compromise of 1897 had revived the French
            Liberal party in Manitoba, which needed an official organ. Its program was simple: “our
            race, our language, our religion”. The last issue was published on July 20, 1905, when
            its editor Henri d’Hellencourt left Manitoba for Québec.</history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Winnipeg Citizen</name>
        <sortName>Winnipeg Citizen</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>TWC</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="5" day="19" year="1919"/>
            <end month="6" day="20" year="1919"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Winnipeg Citizen a paru tous les jours du 19 mai 1919 au 20 juin
            1919, publié par le Citizens’ Committee of One Thousand durant la grève générale de
            Winnipeg. Il était farouchement opposé à la grève et accusait régulièrement les meneurs
            de la grève d’inciter à la révolution. </history>
        <history lang="en">The Winnipeg Citizen was published daily from May 19, 1919 to June 20,
            1919 Published during Winnipeg General Strike, by Citizen's Committee of One Thousand.
            It was fiercely opposed to the strike and regularly accused the strike leaders of trying
            to start a revolution. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Winnipeg Telegram Strike Editions</name>
        <!--<name>Winnipeg Telegram - Strike Edition</name>-->
        <sortName>Winnipeg Telegram Strike Editions</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>TWT</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="5" day="28" year="1919"/>
            <end month="6" day="28" year="1919"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">
            <p>Le quotidien The Winnipeg Telegram a publié une édition de grève du 28 mai au 28 juin
                1919. Ses numéros spéciaux de grève accusaient les meneurs de la grève d’être des
                bolcheviques révolutionnaires et il était clairement opposé à la grève. </p>
            <p> Nous avons numérisé les éditions de grève du Winnipeg Telegram afin d’appuyer les
                textes thématiques. À titre d’information générale, veuillez noter que le Winnipeg
                Telegram était un quotidien qui a été publié du 22 août 1907 au 16 octobre 1920.
            </p>
        </history>
        <history lang="en">
            <p>Strike editions of the daily Winnipeg Telegram were published from May 28 to June 28,
                1919. Its special strike issues attacked the strike leaders as Bolshevik
                revolutionaries and it was clearly opposed to the strike. </p>
            <p> The strike editions of the Winnipeg Telegram were digitized to support the thematic
                material. As background information, please note that the Winnipeg Telegram
                newspaper was a daily published from August 22, 1907 to October 16, 1920. </p>
        </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Western Labor News</name>
        <sortName>Western Labor News</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>WLN</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="4" day="4" year="1919"/>
            <end month="9" day="5" year="1919"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">
            <p>The Western Labor News a publié une édition de grève tous les jours du 17 mai 1919 au
                23 juin 1919. Il a publié deux éditions trois jours particuliers, soit le 17 mai, le
                17 juin et le 20 juin 1919. Nous avons aussi inclus dans la collection numérisée
                d’autres numéros du Western Labor News qui sont liés à la grève, soit ceux du 4
                avril, du 27 juin et du 5 septembre 1919. </p>
            <p> Nous avons numérisé les éditions de grève du Western Labor News afin d’appuyer les
                textes thématiques. À titre d’information générale, veuillez noter que The Western
                Labor News a remplacé The Voice comme organe du Winnipeg Trades and Labor Council et
                a été publié du 2 août 1918 au 13 avril 1923. </p>
        </history>
        <history lang="en">
            <p>Strike editions of the Western Labor News were published daily from May 17, 1919
                until June 23, 1919. Double editions were published on three separate days, May 17,
                June 17 and June 20, 1919. Strike related Western Labor News issues from April 4,
                June 27 and September 5, 1919 have also been included in this digitized collection. </p>
            <p> The strike editions of the Western Labor News were digitized to support the thematic
                material. As background information, please note that The Western Labor News
                replaced The Voice as the organ of the Winnipeg Trades and Labor Council and was
                published from August 2 1918 to April 13, 1923. </p>
        </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>The Western Star</name>
        <sortName>Western Star</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>TWS</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="6" day="24" year="1919"/>
            <end month="6" day="24" year="1919"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Western Star a paru le 24 juin 1919 seulement. C’était une édition
            spéciale de grève du Western Labor News, lui-même l’organe officiel du Winnipeg Trades
            and Labor Council.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Western Star appeared on June 24, 1919 only as a special strike
            edition of the Western Labor News, itself the official organ of the Winnipeg Trades and
            Labor Council.</history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>The Enlightener</name>
        <sortName>Enlightener</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>TEL</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="6" day="25" year="1919"/>
            <end month="6" day="26" year="1919"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Enlightener a paru les 25 et 26 juin 1919 seulement. C’était une
            édition spéciale de grève du Western Labor News, lui-même l’organe officiel du Winnipeg
            Trades and Labor Council.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Enlightener appeared on June 25 and 26, 1919 only as special strike
            editions of the Western Labor News, itself the official organ of the Winnipeg Trades and
            Labor Council.</history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>The Winnipeg Socialist</name>
        <sortName>Winnipeg Socialist</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>SOC</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="5" day="1" year="1921"/>
            <end month="5" day="1" year="1921"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Winnipeg Socialist était publié une fois par mois par le local 5 du
            Parti socialiste du Canada. Son édition de grève a paru le 1er mai 1921.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Winnipeg Socialist was published monthly by Local No. 5 of the
            Socialist Party of Canada. Its strike edition appeared on May 1, 1921. </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>One Big Union</name>
        <sortName>One Big Union</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>OBU</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="8" day="30" year="1919"/>
            <end month="8" day="30" year="1919"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">
            <p>The One Big Union Bulletin était l’organe officiel du mouvement de la One Big Union.
                Il était publié par le Winnipeg Central Labor Council de la OBU. Un numéro spécial
                sur la grève générale a paru le 30 août 1919. </p>
            <p> Nous avons numérisé l’édition de grève du Bulletin pour appuyer le texte thématique.
                À titre d’information générale, veuillez noter que le One Big Union Bulletin a été
                publié une fois par semaine du 12 août 1919 au 24 mai 1934. </p>
        </history>
        <history lang="en">
            <p>The One Big Union Bulletin was the official organ of the One Big Union movement. It
                was published by the Winnipeg Central Labor Council of the O.B.U. One special issue
                about the General Strike appeared on August 30, 1919. </p>
            <p> The strike edition of the Bulletin was digitized to support the thematic material.
                As background information, please note that the One Big Union Bulletin was published
                weekly from August 12, 1919 to May 24, 1934. </p>
        </history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Strikers Defense Bulletin</name>
        <sortName>Strikers Defense Bulletin</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>SDB</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="8" year="1919"/>
            <end month="8" year="1919"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">The Strikers Defense Bulletin a été publié pour présenter la cause des
            grévistes qui avaient été arrêtés. Il en existe un numéro, celui du 27 août 1919, dans
            la collection de la Bibliothèque de l’Assemblée législative.</history>
        <history lang="en">The Strikers Defense Bulletin was published to present the case of the
            strikers who had been arrested. One issue, August 27, 1919, from the Legislative
            Library's holdings exists.</history>
    </newspaper>
    <newspaper lang="en">
        <name>Manitoba Free Press</name>
        <sortName>Manitoba Free Press</sortName>
        <codes>
            <code>MFP</code>
        </codes>
        <pubDates>
            <start month="11" day="30" year="1872"/>
            <end month="5" day="18" year="1878"/>
        </pubDates>
        <history lang="fr">Le 9 novembre 1872, un prospectus gratuit a été distribué dans toute la
            province « dans le but de donner aux gens un spécimen de notre journal ». Sa devise
            était : « Liberté des échanges – Liberté de religion – Égalité des droits civils ». Les
            éditeurs William F. Luxton et John A. Kenny expliquaient que le journal était imprimé
            sur « la première presse à imprimer mécanique jamais amenée au nord-ouest de St. Paul,
            Minnesota. » L’hebdomadaire a commencé à paraître le 30 novembre 1872 et a été publié
            tous les samedis jusqu’au 18 mai 1878 sous le nom de Manitoba Free Press. Il a ensuite
            continué sous le nom de Manitoba Weekly Free Press.</history>
        <history lang="en">On November 9, 1872 a free prospectus was circulated throughout the
            province "with the object of giving the people a specimen of our journal." Its motto was
            "Freedom in trade - Liberty in religion - Equality in civil rights." The publishers
            William F. Luxton and John A. Kenny explained that it was printed on "the first power
            printing press ever brought northwest of St. Paul, Minn." The weekly newspaper started
            publishing every Saturday on November 30, 1872 continuing until May 18, 1878 under the
            title Manitoba Free Press. It then continued under the title Manitoba Weekly Free Press.
        </history>
    </newspaper>
		<newspaper>
			<name>The Winnipeg Tribune</name>
			<sortName>Winnipeg Tribune</sortName>
			<codes>
				<code>WPT</code>
			</codes>
			<pubDates>
				<start year="1890"/>
				<end year="1980"/>
			</pubDates>
			<history lang="en">The Winnipeg Tribune, one of western Canada's oldest newspapers, ran from 1890 to 1980. The Tribune was a rival to the Winnipeg Free Press. While it had excellent coverage of local events and personalities, it also reported on national and international news.</history>
			<history lang="fr">La Winnipeg Tribune était un des plus anciens journaux de l'ouest canadien. Publiée entre 1890 et 1980, elle rivalisait avec la Winnipeg Free Press, journal qui existe encore aujourd'hui. Les reportages sur les événements et personnages d'importance locale étaient excellents, sans pourtant négliger les nouvelles d'ordre national ou international.</history>
		</newspaper>
	<newspaper>
		<name>The Manitoban</name>
		<sortName>Manitoban</sortName>
		<codes>
			<code>The_Manitoban</code>
		</codes>
		<pubDates>
			<start month="11" day="5" year="1914"/>
			<end />
		</pubDates>
		<history lang="en">The Manitoban began publication in 1914 as the official newspaper for University of Manitoba students.   It has a variable publication schedule, but in general has been published weekly during the school year and sporadically over the summer.  It was formerly published by the University of Manitoba Students' Union, but latterly has been published by the Manitoban Newspaper Publications Corporation, an independent organization.</history>
		<history lang="fr">The Manitoban began publication in 1914 as the official newspaper for University of Manitoba students.   It has a variable publication schedule, but in general has been published weekly during the school year and sporadically over the summer.  It was formerly published by the University of Manitoba Students' Union, but latterly has been published by the Manitoban Newspaper Publications Corporation, an independent organization.</history>
	</newspaper>
</newspaper_histories>
